Okay, good morning. Today's דף daf is י"ח. Yud-Ches. We start with
the משנה. Mishnah. We are done for the moment between מדות Middot
and תמיד Tamid discussions, a little less structural and more action.
And we are moving to now the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol leading
into יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So before we said that during the
whole week he was doing the regular עבודות, avodot, and that's got
lots of discussions of exactly the order of the נרות nerot and
the קטרת. ketoret. Now we are getting really to ערב יום כיפור,
Erev Yom Kippur, ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, and special things
done because it's about to be יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So let's
take a look. משנה Mishnah on י"ח. Yud-Ches. מסרו לו זקנים מזקני
בית דין. Masru lo zekeinim mizekinei Beis Din. So was given over
to him elders from the elders of בית דין. Beis Din. So
who gave them over, but it means like the next stage in
the process were that he now was under the auspices of some
elders of בית דין Beis Din and they were handling him from
here on. בית דין. Beis Din. Now again, as we've mentioned before,
it came up a lot in שקלים, Shekalim, right? So the גמרא's
Gemara assumption that like everything that went on ultimately, you know, even
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, even what the כהנים Kohanim were
doing, even the leadership of the כהנים, Kohanim, ultimately was under the
auspices of בית דין. Beis Din. I mean, it sort of never
discusses like the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know, and his relationship.
I mean here he is the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know,
but he's more being like trained in terms of like, you know,
him exercising his power and how that relates to בית דין. Beis
Din. I don't know of anything that really sort of, you know,
sort of positions those two. But, because if you think about it,
the major sort of locations of power, this is really what Soloveitchik
talks about, is בית דין, Beis Din, right, the court system, if
you would, the rabbinic system, you know, the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
and the king, political system. So, the גמרא Gemara assumes that pretty
much anything that took place in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you
know, was under the auspices of בית דין. Beis Din. So that's
what we have here in our משנה. Mishnah. So let's take a
look. Soloveitchik makes the point that, you know, and it was sort
of implicit what I was saying, but that בית דין Beis Din
obviously is not just in terms of adjudication and not even just
in terms of like, you know, interpreting of the law of the
תורה, Torah, but it is also בית דין Beis Din often functions
as a representative for כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Like when the elders
of בית דין Beis Din go out, right, ויצאו זקניך ושפטיך, veyatzu
zekanecha ve'shoftecha, similar
thing, elders of בית דין Beis Din and they go out for
the עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, what they are doing there is they
are sort of representing the people. So Soloveitchik,
you know, makes that point in a number of places, and this
being one of them, that the idea here is that בית דין
Beis Din as the representatives of the people, you know, and therefore
what the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is going to do on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur ultimately is for the sake of and on behalf
of the people. But, you know, you could say and we'll see
in a minute that it's also, you know, בית דין Beis Din
again, not as the adjudicating body, but as representatives of תורה Torah
and תורה Torah authority. And those are different things, right? When בית
דין Beis Din goes out for the עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, they're
not representing תורה Torah authority as much as they are representing the
people. So it's worth thinking about the sort of, the symbolic role,
you know, and the representative role that בית דין Beis Din is
playing. Though, you had another question?
Two short questions. One is in the משנה, Mishnah, מסרו לו זקנים,
masru lo zekeinim, it means מסרו אותו? masru oso?
No, meaning the מסרו masru is the anonymous, meaning it was given
over to him elders from זקני בית דין. ziknei Beis Din. So
who gave it over is anonymous. They.
זקנים zekanim is the object.
זקנים zekanim is a direct object and not the subject of the
verb.
זקנים zekanim is the object of the verb. The subject is not
stated.
Okay.
Right. This idea of representative of the people, כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael,
is that related in some way רב קוק Rav Kook had this
religious Zionist idea that the government of the State of Israel had
the status of מלכות, malchut, of מלך, melech, in some continuum with
the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? Yeah, yeah.
It's related, it's related. Okay. וקוראים לפניו בסדר היום, Vekorin lefanav b'seder
hayom, and they read in front of him the order of the
day. Now the phrase וקוראים לפניו korin lefanav and we'll see the
next phrase suggests it's not like they read from a manual and
a how-to and עבודת יום הכפורים Avodas Yom HaKippurim for Dummies, but
they just took out the תורה. Torah. The word וקוראים korin suggests
they read the פסוקים pesukim of the תורה, Torah, which is interesting
because of course it's not all explicit in the פסוקים pesukim of
the תורה Torah and there are things that maybe are not even
so much like the פשט p'shat of the פסוקים pesukim here and
there. So it's interesting this idea that they, which it seems to
be the פשט p'shat is that they read the סדר היום seder
hayom from the תורה. Torah. ואומרים לו, Ve'omrim lo, and they would
say to him, אישי כהן גדול, Ishi Kohen Gadol, Mr. כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, קרא אתה בפיך, k'ra attah be'ficha, read on your own,
read the פסוקים pesukim in the תורה. Torah. שמא שכחת, Shemma shachachta,
maybe you forgot how it was done, או שמא לא למדת, o
shemma lo lamad'ta, or maybe you never learned. So obviously that reflects
a pretty significant level of ignorance that the גמרא Gemara will get
to. So that's what they would do. ערב יום הכיפורים שחרית. Erev
Yom HaKippurim Shacharit. Now again, so it sounds like this first line
was before ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, but again, it's not
clear, it doesn't, also you don't get the sense it was every
day of the seven days. So it's not exactly clear when that
reading happened. But anyway, now we are in ערב יום כיפור Erev
Yom Kippur proper. ערב יום הכיפורים שחרית, Erev Yom HaKippurim Shacharit, מעמידים
אותו בשער המזרח, ma'amidim oto be-Sha'ar Hamizrach, they, again the anonymous they.
You know, the better way to stand would be he was made
to stand, but by the eastern gate, so by the שער ניקנור,
Sha'ar Nicanor, the opening to the עזרה, Azarah, ומעבירין לפניו פרים ואילים
וכבשים. uma'avirin lefanav parim ve-eilim u-kevasim. And they would march in front
of
him cows, or excuse me, oxen, rams, and sheep, כדי שיהא מכיר
ורגיל בעבודה, kedei sheyehei makhir ve-ragil ba'avodah, so he should recognize them
and be familiar and how to do the עבודה. avodah. Now the
מהרש"א Maharsha points out that this does not mean, like the גמרא
Gemara is going to comment on the fact that, you know, he
might have been a little bit of an ignoramus when the כהונה,
kehunah, when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol role was bought and sold.
But nevertheless, it's not like he never saw a cow before in
his life, right? I mean these were more of a rural society
regardless. Not like, I mean, even I know the difference between a
cow and a ram and a sheep. So it wasn't that he
was telling him look, this is a cow, it's, you know, but
what it was doing to him was basically what the מהרש"א Maharsha
says, I had sort of been speculating this and then I checked
and the מהרש"א Maharsha says the same thing. He says that they
were doing the roleplay. They actually were not just saying this is
a cow. They were saying this is a cow. Now walk over
to it. Now pretend you're doing the שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, now walk
over to the ram and take this, and take this over there
and pretend you're doing this. And then take this and do that.
And if you actually not just read it intellectually but act it
out and act it out with some of the real animals, you
know, then it just becomes more like intuitive. You don't have to
say what's next now? Is it the cow? Is it the goat?
Is it the sheep? Right? You've done the roleplay with the actual
animals and you spend... so again, I don't know why they only
do this ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. If there would be
anything to be doing the week leading up, you could see that
you would want to do this every single day of the week
leading up so by the time it gets to be יום כיפור
Yom Kippur it's second nature. But that's what they would do. כל
שבעת הימים. Kol shivat hayamim. There are those, I don't know if
I really see this so much, but there is a couple of
modern interpretations, I'm trying to remember who said it, that want to
see that this is also a little bit of a reenactment of
מעשה בראשית. Ma'aseh Bereishit. You know, that the אדם Adam is in
the garden and he goes and the animals are brought before him
and he names the animals. It doesn't say here he named the
animals, you know, so it's a little bit of a stretch. But
you know, when we do say the עבודה avodah in on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur itself, we start with מעשה בראשית. Ma'aseh Bereishit. I
don't know if people know, right? Which is God created the world,
that's the beginning of the עבודה. avodah. Right? And then you talk
about, you know, אדם Adam and the and נח Noach and the
flood and, you know, אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak ve-Ya'akov and then,
you know, then you have לוי Levi and the כהנים Kohanim and
then and then אהרן הכהן Aharon HaKohen and then you get to
the עבודה. avodah. Right? So it does start with the whole story
of, you know, of the creation story. So anyway, some want to
make that connection. כל שבעת הימים לא היו מונעים ממנו מאכל ומשתה.
Kol shivat hayamim lo hayu mon'in mimenu ma'achal u-mishteh.
All seven days they would not withhold from him food and drink.
He can eat and drink whatever he wants. ערב יום הכיפורים עם
חשיכה. Erev Yom HaKippurim im chasheichah. ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur
as it was getting dark, meaning as it was turning, you know,
לא היו מניחין אותו לאכול הרבה מפני שהמאכל מביא את השינה. lo
hayu manichin oto leechol harbeh mipnei shehama'achal meivi et hasheinah. So right
there ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur when everybody else is having
their, you know, סעודה המפסקת se'udah hamafseket and eating a good amount
to prepare themselves for the fast that's coming up. So, I mean,
it's meaning it's almost about to be יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, he
would actually eat a smaller amount. He would not eat a lot
right before nightfall of יום כיפור Yom Kippur because you do not
want him to fall asleep. He would have to be up the
whole night ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur leading into, and we'll
see because of this concern that were he to fall asleep, he
would have a seminal emission and he would become טמא tamei and
that would be a obviously a problem and you'd have to get
the backup guy. So it actually would be doing the עבודה avodah
the next day on no sleep the night before. All right, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Now so the גמרא
Gemara says the following: בשלמא שמא שכח, לחיי. Bishlama shemashachach, lechai.
To say that maybe you forgot how to do the עבודה, avodah,
געזונטהייט, gezuntheit, that's a technical translation of לחיי. lechai. אלא שמא לא
למד? Ella shema lo lamad?
I can understand that he forgot, but he never learned it? He
never read the פרשה parsha of אחרי מות? Acharei Mot? מי מוקמינן
כי האי גוונא? Mi mokminan ki hai gavna?
When would you ever have a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who had
never learned the עבודה? avodah? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraita, והכהן הגדול מאחיו, vehakohen hagadol me'echav,
the כהן Kohen who is greater from his brethren, right? It's a
way of referring to the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, right? גדול Gadol
there is the word. So the phrase הגדול מאחיו hagadol me'echav is
read to say the following: שיהא גדול מאחיו, sheyehei gadol me'echav,
that if you're appointing a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you have to
pick one that is greater than the alternatives, greater than the other
כהנים. Kohanim. In what way greater? בכח. Bekoach. So that's quite fascinating.
Physical strength, right? As a sort of as a, you know, as
a way of demonstrating authority and power. I mean, you could try
to say technically if you're strong you can shlep big pieces of
animals up the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but I think more this is talking
about like the impression that we have of leadership and authority and
so on. you know, and somebody is tall, and people all know
this, right, that people that are tall are more,
the presidents, of CEOs of major corporations tend to be much taller
than your average person, and these sort of types of physical characteristics,
although they've obviously shown that there's no actual correlation, as if that
were a חידוש chidush between any of these things and actual leadership
ability, nevertheless, you know, these types of things are the ways that
impress people with a sense of authority and of leadership. So that
he's greater in physical strength, בנוי benoy in appearance, you know, beauty
and in appearance, good-looking, tall, strong, okay, and בחכמה bechochma wisdom, okay,
actually he's more intelligent,
ובעושר u'be'osher and wealth, right? So all of those things are things
that embody that sense of greatness and authority, at least, at least
in the eyes of people. אחרים אומרים, acherim omrim, others say, מנין
שאם אין לו שאחיו הכהנים מגדלים אותו. minayin she'im ein lo she'achav
hakohanim megadlin oto. How do you know that if he does not
have
wealth, you know, obviously they can't do these other things for him,
but the things that they can give him is money. So how
do you know if you found the right כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and the only problem is is that he's not wealthy, that you
basically have to get donations from the other כהנים Kohanim and make
him wealthy? תלמוד לומר והכהן הגדול מאחיו גדלהו משל אחיו. talmud lomar
vehakohen hagadol me'achav gadlehu mishel achav.
You can make him great from his brothers. So if they can
help, if you found the right candidate and the only thing that
he's missing is something that the other כהנים Kohanim can help out
with, then you get those contributions from the other כהנים. Kohanim. So
the relevance for us is about how could you suggest that here's
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol supposed to be גדול בחכמה gadol bechochma
and never learned the עבודה avodah of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, especially
if my read is correct that the קוראים לפניו korim lefanav means
you read it from the פסוקים. pesukim. So it's one thing to
say, you know, you don't know the details of it, but you
don't, you've never read the פסוקים? pesukim? Now I have to tell
you, I don't understand why the גמרא Gemara is okay with שכחת,
shachachta, right? So I don't understand where were you in שול shul
last year? What does that mean? I mean, if you really are
גדול בחכמה, gadol bechochma, then how do you get a scenario of
שכחת? shachachta? What, you forgot what's written in אחרי מות? Acharei Mos?
But anyway, maybe you know, maybe he's getting on in years, you
know, his memory is not what it used to be, who knows.
The other interesting question I want to know is, are we assuming
it's his first year doing the service? Because if it, you know,
as long as if it's not his first year, then again, you
don't have, how do you have שכחת? shachachta? Didn't you just do
this last year? So again, you could say if he's really a
little bit of a dolt and he doesn't spend a year doing
עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, or you know, or
maybe his memory isn't what it used to be, it's possible, it's
שכחת. shachachta. But how's, how was it that he never learned? He
never learned the פסוקים, pesukim, he never learned the עבודה? avodah?
You mentioned about בית שני. Bayis Sheni. I know.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is leading up to. I know.
It's leading up to that answer. So it says, אמר רב יוסף
לא קשיא כאן במקדש ראשון כאן במקדש שני. amar Rav Yosef lo
kashya kan be'Mikdash Rishon kan be'Mikdash Sheni. In the בית המקדש ראשון
Beis HaMikdash Rishon we had כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim like we would
have liked them, you know, and they were גדול בחכמה בעושר בכח
gadol bechochma be'osher be'koach the whole thing, and therefore there was never
a concern that they didn't learn it or that they had forgotten
it. בית שני, Bayis Sheni, it's possible you have a real ignoramus
and it's really possible that he never learned it, or that if
he learned it, he learned it once and he forgot it. דאמר
רב אסי de'amar Rav Assi because רב אסי Rav Assi says תרקבא
דדינרי tarkava de'dinari like a basket full of דינרי dinari of gold
coins איילה לה מרתא בת בייתוס aylah lah Martha bas Baithos מרתא
Martha the daughter of בייתוס. Baithos. It's quite interesting that people remember
בייתוס בן זונין Baithos ben Zonin was a very wealthy person, right?
He had a whole bakery factory going on. He has the famous
question about making מצות matzos with cookie cutters and making צורות tzuros
if people remember that. Anyway, בייתוס Baithos was quite wealthy, his name
comes up in places in גמרא. Gemara. So here his daughter, presumably
she inherited some of the estate, so she's wealthy as well. So
a basket full of gold coins, this מרתא בת בייתוס Martha bas
Baithos contributed לינאי מלכא le'Yannai malka to the King Yannai על דאוקמי
ליהושע בן גמלא בכהני רברבי al de'ukmei le'Yehoshua ben Gamla be'khanei ravrevi
for making יהושע בן גמלא Yehoshua ben Gamla the כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Why was she so interested in him being the כהן גדול?
Kohen Gadol? So רש״י Rashi says she was married to him. She
was a widow and she had married him and she was a
wealthy widow.
But if she's a widow, how could she be married to?
Oh, so not she was a, well, that's a good point, so
not a widow, I misstated it.
No, רש״י Rashi says אלמנה, almanah,
רש״י Rashi says אלמנה עשירה הייתה. almanah ashirah haytah. That's an excellent
point! So that's an excellent point. I, you're right. How could a
widow, how could a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol be married to a
widow? Again, you know, would they have glossed over that if you
give a big enough
contribution?
What was that joke about, it was one of those Rabbi jokes
and about buying, you know, I forget anyway, the guy that wants
to be a כהן Kohen and he's ready to make this huge
donation to the שול shul and you know, and fine, I'll lead
a million dollar check for your building fund. Okay, okay, I'll make
you a כהן. Kohen. But why so important? Look, if my grandfather
was a כהן Kohen and my father was a כהן, Kohen, I
want to be a כהן Kohen too. Anyway, fine. So, but that's
an excellent question, you're right that that didn't stop me, but that's
an excellent point. What's רש״י Rashi doing saying she was an אלמנה?
almanah? I mean, I don't know why, why that's even why he,
what motivated him to assert that. There's nothing in the story that
says she was an אלמנה. almanah.
A regular, a regular כהן Kohen can
marry.
Maybe but the fascinating thing is look if the government if it
was a bought position it raises an interesting question could you buy
the position and would the other כהנים Kohanim tolerate? They might not
have a choice you know ultimately what the you know what the
Roman government says goes but you know would they have sometimes to
tolerate somebody that actually would be he's not פסול עבודה pasul avodah
but actually would be violating laws of the כהונה Kehunah you know?
That's an excellent you know being married to a woman he's not
allowed does not invalidate him although that's an interesting question the וכיפר
בעדו ובעד ביתו v'chiper ba'ado u'vead beito would you be able to
say it's יוצא yotzei that category if ביתו beito was ביתו האסורה
לו?
beito ha'asura
lo? Anyway it's very and very interesting point that I didn't think
about in terms of that רש"י. Rashi. יישר כוח. Shkoiach.
So that's what she did. תוספות Tosafot points out this was not
the normal ינאי המלך Yannai HaMelech because based on other גמרות Gemorot
ינאי המלך Yannai HaMelech was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and he
obviously would not have sold it to anybody else. So anyway תוספות
Tosafot claims this was a different ינאי המלך. Yannai HaMelech. Yes.
A regular כהן kohen can marry an אלמנה.
almanah. Yes regular כהן kohen can. But then but then once
he's married to an אלמנה almanah and then becomes כהן גדול kohen
gadol he doesn't have to divorce her does he?
Well he would he'd be in violation. Now it is true that
it's actually a very interesting question the רמב"ם Rambam says as opposed
to ראב"ד Ra'avad all the איסורי עריות issurei arayot are about לא
תקרבו לגלות ערוה lo tikrevu l'galot ervah you know it's about the
act of sex. By the כהנים Kohanim and the people that are
כהנים Kohanim are אסור assur to marry it says you know אלמנה
וגרושה לא יקח almanah u'grusha lo yikach right? So it's an so
the רמב"ם Rambam understands so the ראב"ד Ra'avad understands the איסור issur
is still is still sex but the רמב"ם Rambam understands that the
איסור issur is only is only the act of marriage. I'm trying
to remember if he says it's sex in the context of marriage
as opposed to extra you know if they're not married or if
he דוקא davka says the איסור issur is the act of marriage.
The נפקא מינה nafka mina would be would be this case would
be let's say you're already married if the only איסור issur is
the act of marriage so that's an interesting question according to what
would be what would be the story? Hold on let me see
quickly if I can find you the answer to that. Oh
all of a sudden we
got into a very interesting conversation.
Okay hold on. שלוש נשים
שנסאו לכהן
Shalosh
nashim
shenas'u
l'Kohen
כל כהן שנשא אחת משלוש נשים אלו בין גדול בין הדיוט ובעל
לוקה אם בעל דרך
זנות אינו לוקה משום
זונה גרושה חללה שנאמר לא יקחו עד
שיקח ויבעול.
Kol Kohen shenasa achat mishalosh nashim elu bein
gadol bein hedyot u'va'al lokeh im ba'al derech
zenut eino lokeh mishum zonah
grusha chalala shene'emar lo yikchu ad sheyikach v'yival.
So he actually says it's not just sex it's sex in marriage
but he says part it's two acts עד שיקח ויבעול. ad sheyikach
v'yival. So oh one minute אבל כהן גדול שבעל על אלמנה לוקה
אחת אף על פי שלא
קידש שנאמר לא
יחלל כיוון שבעלה חיללה פסלה לכהונה.
Aval Kohen Gadol sheba'al al almanah lokeh achat af al pi shelo
kidesh shene'emar lo yichalel kivan sheba'ala
chillela pasla l'Kehunah.
Okay. אבל זונה
וחללה וגרושה הרי הן מחוללות ובאות לפיכך אינו לוקה עליהן אלא בביאת
אלמנה לבדה. Aval zonah v'chalala u'grusha harei hen mechulalot u'va'ot lefikach eino
lokeh aleihen ela b'vi'at almanah levada. So even the רמב"ם Rambam who
says that you don't get מלקות malkos without it being in the
context of marriage or maybe without the act of marriage says כהן
גדול kohen gadol with אלמנה almanah is different. So there goes that
answer. So maybe if what? It sounds like if she was already
married to him then it would be okay. If he could marry
an אלמנה almanah of a כהן גדול kohen gadol yeah
but
רש"י Rashi doesn't say that. All right. All right. ערב יום כיפורים
Erev Yom Kippurim so that's the case about מרתא. Martha. By the
way this difference between בית ראשון Bayit Rishon and בית שני Bayit
Sheni I should say
there's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says why are you worried
that he's going to be רואה קרי roeh keri like have a
seminal emission at night? We teach that
one of the ניסים nissim of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was
that the כהן גדול kohen gadol like never saw you know never
had a seminal emission. So there are two answers. One answer is
basically אין סומכין על הנס ein somchin al haness answer okay and
the you know you do what you can in humanly to make
it happen. And the other answer is בית ראשון Bayit Rishon בית
שני Bayit Sheni that those that נס ness only happened in בית
ראשון. Bayit Rishon. So but so again that idea that there was
this you know ירידה yeridah and we have to be more on
our toes. Okay, so they had him read the עבודה, avodah,
either he never learned it or he forgot it. Again, it's interesting,
it sounds like reading some of the פסוקים pesukim as opposed to
reading from some book that actually gives you the step-by-step, okay, and
now we're going to talk about the walking the animal, the parading
of the animals. ערב יום הכיפורים שחרית, Erev Yom Kippurim Shacharis, תניא,
tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, אף השעירים, af hase'irim, they
would also walk before him the goats. תנא דידן מאי טעמא לא
תני שעירים, Tana didan mai ta'ama lo tani se'irim, why does our
משנה mishnah not mention the goat? So כיון דעל חטא קאתי, keivan
d'al cheit ka-asi, since they are coming for the sin, right? The
goats, one is the goat that gets pushed over the cliff and
the other is the one that's brought, you know, that they do
the blood like they do the blood of the כהן גדול's Kohen
Gadol's פר, par, so therefore the sin of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael,
חלשא דעתיה. chalsha da'atiah. He would become like, he would become weak,
he would
despair thinking about all the sins of the people that are riding
on his shoulders. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, ee hachi,
if we don't want to do goats because it would despair him
and make him think of the sin, פר נמי, par nami, what
do you mean, his ox, נמי על חטא הוא דאתי, nami al
cheit hu d'asi, that's coming for a sin. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, פר, par, the ox, כיון דעליו ועל אחוה הכהנים הוא
דאתי, keivan d'alav v'al echav hakoanim hu d'asi, it's coming for him
and his fellow כהנים, kohanim, so באחוה הכהנים אי
איכא איניש דאית ביה מילתא, b'echav hakoanim ee ika inish d'is bei
milsa, if there is amongst his fellow כהנים kohanim people that are,
you know, sinners, has a thing meaning has like sins that they're
not repenting for,
bad actions, מידע ידע ליה, meida yada lei, he's aware of it,
you know, because it's all within the family, ומהדר ליה בתשובה, u'mahader
lei b'teshuva, and he actually will have a whole conversation with him,
bring him into his office on ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur
and tell him he has to do תשובה. teshuva. ובכולו ישראל לא
ידע, U'vechulu Yisrael lo yada, but in terms of the larger Jewish
people, who does he know who the sinners are? So he has
more of a sense of despondency when he thinks about being מכפר
mechaper for the sins of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Now of course
it's a little funny because the כהנים, kohanim, it's not like he's
saying his immediate family, it's not like even saying his hundred closest
relatives, talking about all the כהנים, kohanim, you know, again, maybe if
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was always in the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, you know, and always serving there, he would get to know
the כהנים, kohanim, you know, because he's always there, he gets to
see all of the rotations. Even so though, you really only see,
you know, any particular כהן kohen like four times a year because
they only come to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash twice a year,
it's a twenty-four sort of group rotation, and even that week that
they're there, any particular כהן kohen only serves one day of the
week and on שבת. Shabbos. So how much do you really get
to know all of the כהנים? kohanim? Anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara's
answer, that at least he feels that more it's not like it's
out of his control. Yes, I have to atone for them, again,
maybe you could even say it a little bit more hypothetically. Yes,
I have to atone for them, but at least I know that
if I were to find somebody that wasn't doing תשובה teshuva I'd
be able to have influence on them, I'd be able to find
out about it, he feels more in control, you know, if you
have a greater sense of confidence about what's going on. Whereas by
the rest of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, you know, he had absolutely
no control over them. So אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, says רבינא, Ravina,
היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu d'amri inshi, that's what people say, אי בר
אחתיך דיילא, ee bar achasach daila, if your nephew is a, is
basically like a, like a tax collector, you know, an officer of
the king, הוי
חזי בשוקא קמיה לא תחלוף, havi chazi b'shuka kamei lo sachloof, and
if he appears before you in the marketplace, don't walk in front
of him. Because, meaning if your nephew works for the IRS, then
you better be very careful about your taxes. Meaning they know all,
they know how much money you've got, your family, they know all
your tricks, they know what you're up to, so you don't want
to mess with a member of your family that has some authority.
All right, so that's the, so that's the answer
about that. So now I have to tell you, if we're doing
actually like role play, it really is a big deal not to
do the goats. I mean, half of the whole focus is with
the goats. שחיטת השעיר, Shechitas hasa'ir, then you שחט shacht the goat,
then you send the goat over the cliff and da da da
da, and you do the whole drawing of the לוט. lot. It
seems a little bit crazy to try to do the role play
without the goats, right? So it's quite fascinating this answer that they
didn't do the goats because it would make him feel despairing when
he thought about the sins of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael on that,
the
sins that he had no sort of control over. The other interesting
thing which we'll get to in the eighth פרק perek is how
much is the תשובה teshuva of people a necessary component of the
כפרה kaparah when you have the קרבנות. korbanos. Meaning our focus without
the קרבנות korbanos is on תשובה, teshuva, but when there were קרבנות,
korbanos, whether תשובה teshuva was really necessary or not to achieve כפרה
kaparah is a, is a very important discussion that comes up later
and not everybody thinks that תשובה teshuva was necessary when there was
the presence of the קרבנות. korbanos. So again, this idea of introducing
these concerns about he's anxious about their sins and he won't be
able to make them do תשובה teshuva and all these types of
things, it's quite a fascinating way of sort of framing his, you
know, you know, the,
his sense of his effectiveness and what it means to be bringing
the קרבן. korban. Okay, but that's the answer about why it does
not mention the goats. כל שבעת הימים לא ימנעו, Kol shivas hayamim
lo yimne'u, now we get to this concern about him actually having
seminal emissions. The whole seven days they would not withhold from him
food. but they would not let him eat right before nightfall because
they wanted him to stay up the whole night. So the משנה
Mishna. *mishna* is like this. תניא *Tanya*, we taught in the ברייתא
*braita*, רבי יהודה Yehuda בן נקוסא אמר *Rabbi Yehuda ben Nakusa amar*,
מאכילין אותו סולת וביצים כדי להמססו *maachilin oto solet uveitzim kedei lehamssu*,
that you basically give him flour products and eggs, so you give
him like cakes I guess, anyway that will help make him,
what's the word? It's a diuretic essentially and that'll cleanse him of
food so again he won't be,
he won't have food in his stomach, I mean again it's a
little bit crazy that this is what we're doing before יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur* is we're limiting his food intake and doing
what's called a purgative, a purgative, is that what it's called when
you take what to get no to get the stuff out of
your stomach? A laxative. Anyway, so רש"י Rashi's *Rashi* says the concern
here is so he wouldn't have to go to the bathroom in
the middle of the עבודה avoda. *avoda*, so you get it all
out beforehand. So אמרו לו *amru lo*, they said to him, כל
שכן שאתה מביאו לידי חימום *kol sheken sheata mevio lidei chimum*. No,
that's worse because those are the types of foods that lead to
heat, meaning heat meaning that lead to sexual thoughts and that will
lead to or the body just physiologically responding to them and will
lead to seminal emission. תניא *Tanya*, we taught in the ברייתא *braita*,
סומכוס אמר משום רבי מאיר *Sumchus amar mishum Rabbi Meir*, אין מאכילין
אותו לא עב"י *ein maachilin oto lo avi*. You don't feed him
on ערב יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Erev Yom Kippur* עב"י *avi*. It's
an acronym, we'll see what it means in a minute. ואמרי לה
לא אבב"י *v'amri lah lo avavi*. ויש אומרים אף לא יין לבן
*v'yesh omrim af lo yayin lavan*, even not white wine. So what
are these things? לא עב"י, לא אתרוג *lo avi, lo etrog*, no
etrogs, ולא ביצים beitzim *velo beitzim*, no eggs, ולא יין velo yayin,
ישן *velo yayin yashan*, and old wine. Presumably these are things, citrus
fruits let's say and eggs and wine, these are things that the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* understood would lead to seminal emission. ואמרי לה לא
אבב"י *v'amri lah lo avavi*, so that's adding another ב *bet*, לא
אתרוג ולא ביצים ולא בשר שמן *lo etrog velo beitzim velo basar
shamen*, fatty meat, ולא יין ישן *velo yayin yashan*. ויש אומרים *v'yesh
omrim*, some say, אף לא יין לבן *af lo yayin lavan*, even
white wine is included, מפני שהיין לבן מביא את האדם לידי טומאה
tumah, *mipnei shehayayin lavan mevia et haadam lidei tumah* because that brings
a person to impurity, which here means seminal emission. Again, it's interesting
because presumably that was the concern about all of those, why it
just says it here by the one I don't know. Again, by
the way I should mention it's not obvious that the reason this
was a concern only on ערב יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur* is
because if it was any previous day this is a one day
טומאה *tumah*, you can go to the מקוה *mikveh* and still be
ready for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, but if it was on ערב
יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur* then you're stuck.
Was he including cheese? Why for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*?
Correct. So the whole week before, that was an earlier גמרא gemara
*Gemara*, he was separated from his wife.
But they wouldn't let him sleep anyway on the day before.
Yeah that's a good question.
Being probably too... the day before. Yeah, good point. They wouldn't let
him sleep so how would this happen?
Yeah, in the משנה Mishna. *mishna* it says overeating and over-drinking brings
לידי זיבה ziva *lidei ziva*.
Well we're about to get to that next line right here. תנו
רבנן Rabbanan, *Tanu rabanan*. So now we taught because this is exactly
this issue of what things might cause various types of penile emissions
is a concern that the משנה Mishnah *mishna* that we have when
we're dealing with somebody being a בעל קרי ba'al keri *baal keri*
or a זב *zav*, a man. So זב תולין לו במאכל ובכל
מיני מאכל *zav tolin lo bemaachal uvechol minei maachal*. So here's the
הלכה Halakha *halacha*. If a man has a seminal emission, it doesn't
matter what led to it, whether he was having sexual thoughts, whether
it was just something that happened at night that he can't pin
some causation to, whether it's somebody's foods that the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
says has an effect, doesn't matter. If you have a seminal emission,
you're בעל קרי *baal keri*, you're טמא tamei, *tamei*. But a זב
*zav*, which is a type of a penile emission which is not
semen, some sort of identify it with gonorrhea, some type of a
flow that is not semen, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* has an understanding
that a זב *zav* cannot be מחמת אונס *machmat ones*, cannot be
due to some external cause. Okay, so an external cause is identified
for example as if he had sexual thoughts and then he had
this flow, not a seminal flow, but he had this flow, then
he's not a זב *zav*. Or if he ate certain foods that
bring about, that can bring about these types of things, he's not
a זב *zav* that it's seen as an external cause. What's interesting
is again this assumption that although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is very
clear that as opposed to a woman, the difference between נדה Niddah
*niddah* and זבה *zavah* it's all blood, the difference is the time
of the month, for a man the difference is the nature of
the flow, whether it's semen or something else. So although it's very
clear in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that we're not dealing with semen,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that similar things that cause a seminal
emission can cause this: sexual thoughts, certain foods and so on, okay
even though we're not talking here about semen. So it says the
following: זב תולין לו במאכל ובכל מיני מאכל *zav tolin lo bemaachal
uvechol minei maachal*. If you can hang it, meaning you can attribute
it to
food and all types of food, which means that if he ate
a lot then you can assume it's all because of the food
regardless of the actual food that he ate. אלעזר בן פנחס אומר
משום רבי יהודה בן בתירה *Elazar ben Pinchas omer mishum Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira*, אין מאכילין אותו לא חגב"י ולא גב"ם velo gabam, *ein
maachilin oto lo chagavi velo gabam*, ולא כל דברים המביאין לידי טומאה
velo kol devarim hamavi'in lidei tumah, *velo kol devarim hamevi'in lidei tumah*.
So again we have the same idea of acronyms and the phrase
מביאין לידי טומאה *mevi'in lidei tumah*. So when you are checking him
to make sure, you know, to sort of because he also like
the same way a woman who becomes a זבה *zavah* has to
have clean days, seven days that she's not bleeding, a man who
became a זב *zav* has to have days that he's no longer...
having to flow. So he says when you are checking him and
trying to make sure that he's not having the flow for seven
days, you don't want to be feeding him types of foods that
are going to bring to other types of continual emission. So what
are these things? לא חגבי, לא חלב lo chalav milk, ולא גבינה
velo gevina and cheese, so dairy products. ולא ביצה velo beitza ולא
יין, so egg and wine. So again assuming there's some relation between
these foods, this idea of concern of leading to זיבה and the
other concern about leading to זרע, zera, שכבת זרע, shichvat zera, there's
the overlap of the eggs and the wine with the new addition
of dairy products. ולא גב"ם, מי גריסין של פול mei gerisin shel
pol some type
of a soup of a pounded bean. ובשר שמנה, uvasar shamena, so
fatty meat we mentioned before. ומורייס umaryas which is a type of
a fish hash. Okay, so more foods than were mentioned before. But
here again the concern is not just seminal emission, it's other types
of flow as well.
ולא כל דברים המביאין לידי טומאה, things that bring to impurity. לאתויי
מאי, le'atuyei mai, what does that include? So לאתויי הא דתנו רבנן,
le'atuyei ha detanu rabanan, the rabbis taught, חמישה דברים מביאים את האדם
לידי טומאה. chamisha devarim mevi'im et ha'adam lidei tumah. Now here we're
clearly talking about about שכבת זרע. shichvat zera. We're no longer talking
about this flow, this זוב zov flow, we're talking about seminal emission
because that is the concern of the, when you're not in מסכת
זבים, masechet zavim, the concern of the גמרא Gemara about being a
בעל קרי is not just ritually being טמא, but that the גמרא
Gemara did not like the idea of seminal emission outside of the
context of marital sex. So five things bring to טומאה, meaning can
lead to seminal emission. What are they? ואלו הן, ve'elu hen, השום
hashum a garlic, והשחלים vehashachalim which שחלים shachalim I looked this up,
I don't know what it is, Rashi says cress, and I assume
he means cress, okay,
והחלגלוגות vehachalglogot which I have no idea what that is, what the
people have in English?
Purslane, yeah, that's the word I saw also when I looked it
up. Now it makes total sense. What? והביצים vehabeitzim you have another
word, eggs, והגרגיר vehagargir and גרגיר gargir which the Mesorah says it
was a garden rocket, at least that's one translation I have. What
do you think, say there, Joe? Rocket. What?
Rocket. Garden rocket. Arugula. Arugula?
Oh, arugula! גרגיר gargir arugula, that's interesting. Okay, and now we're going
to talk about arugula or גרגיר gargir for a minute.
Okay. ויצא אחד לשדה vayetze echad lasadeh person went out to the
field ללקט אורות lelaket orot to gather אורות. orot. So what's אורות?
orot? So תנא משמיה דרבי מאיר tana mishmei de'Rabbi Meir זה גרגיר,
zeh gargir, this is this arugula or garden rocket. אמר רבי יוחנן
amar Rabbi Yochanan למה נקרא שמן
אורות, lama nikra sheman orot, why are they called אורות? orot? שמאירות
את העיניים sheme'irot et ha'einayim because it's good for the eyesight. Okay,
so you should eat this, it'll be good for your eyes,
it'll bring light to your eyes. אמר רב הונא amar Rav Huna
המוצא גרגיר, hamotzeh gargir, if you find arugula, like growing wild in
the field, אם יכול לאכלו אוכלו, im yachol le'achlo ochlo, if you're
able to eat it, maybe I don't know because it's a little
bitter, right? Arugula is that like reddish type of a lettuce? No.
Not red, but bitter.
What does it look like? It's
like parsley? Parsley? Okay. All right. So if you're able to eat
it, meaning it's you're able to tolerate it, then eat it, and
it'll be good for you health-wise. ואם לא ve'im lo and if
not, מעבירו על גבי עיניו ma'aviro al gabei einav since it's good
for eyesight, so just rub it across your eyes and that'll help
your eyesight even without eating it. So אמר רב פפא amar Rav
Papa בגרגירא דמצרא, begargira dematzra, this is only by the גרגיר gargir
that grows on the at the edge of the field somehow that
doesn't get the nutrient, it doesn't get anything from any other plants
and therefore it's more in its pure form, that's the way Rashi
explains it. אמר רב גידל אמר רב, amar Rav Gidal amar Rav,
now that we're talking about things that lead to seminal emission, back
to that, so we'll talk about a practical application of that. אכסנאי
achsanai besides just mention you shouldn't be eating it because the גמרא
Gemara doesn't want to have seminal emissions. So now we're talking about
related issue. אמר רב גידל אמר רב amar Rav Gidal amar Rav
אכסנאי achsanai if you're a guest at somebody's house, לא יאכל ביצים
lo yochel beitzim don't eat eggs, because we already spoke about the
fact that eggs bring on seminal emission. Why? Because don't eat ביצים
presumably maybe that was the greatest concern, but don't eat things that
are going to lead to you having a seminal emission at night
because you're sleeping on somebody else's bed and somebody else's sheets and
they'll see it in the morning and that'll be something that'll be
embarrassing for you. So be careful about that when you're in somebody
else's bed. ולא יישן בטליתו של
בעל הבית, velo yishan betalito shel ba'al habayit, and they didn't, it
wasn't like they necessarily always go to the closet and have a
dozen extra blankets. So if you're over at somebody's house, he'll say,
here, use my coat as a blanket, my טלית, talit, my cloak
as a blanket. Don't do that. Because if you use his cloak
as a blanket and you have seminal emission on it, again it'll
be very obvious. Okay, so that would not be wise.
Rashi says or sounds like Rashi the concern might be the opposite,
that maybe the seminal emission is on his cloak from him and
then it would be embarrassing to him. that you would sort of
have his cloak and see what's on the inside of his cloak
if he ever had a seminal emission while wearing his cloak. Okay,
so where are we? רב, Rav, now רב, Rav,
where are we? Sorry, okay. רב Rav כי מקלע לדרשיש ki makla
le-Darshish מכריז, makhriz, so now we have all this concern about being
a guest and not being at
home and seminal emissions. So now we'll see how this story connects.
רב, Rav, when he dropped by in דרשיש, Darshish, presumably some of
these rabbis went on tours of the countryside or tours of the
land, teaching תורה, Torah, answering שאלות, shaylos, whatever they did. So it's
a fascinating thing in itself, the fact of the rabbis who would
travel. We know they would travel to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but
the fact that they would generally travel for what purposes, you know,
that's an interesting area of discussion. So when רב Rav came to
דרשיש, Darshish, מכריז, makhriz, he would make the following announcement: מאן הויה
ליומא? Man havya leyoma? Who would like to be with me for
today? Meaning what woman would like to be my wife of the
day? Okay, so this is dealing with the fact about men away
from home and dealing with their sexual desire. So before we spoke
about being a guest at somebody's house and a concern of seminal
emission, so here we're talking about also being away from home and
dealing with his sexual desire. And his solution, well, the point is
he you might call it that but his point was he wasn't
going to go to a prostitute. He was looking for somebody that
would marry him and be his wife of the day. Oh, so
that's a good point. I mean, you're right. Just for a day,
he doesn't yeah, well, I'm reading it in terms of the next
discussion in the גמרא. Gemara That's the lens through which the גמרא
Gemara reads it. It's an interesting question whether it's possible to have
read that even not in the context of marriage, but that's not
the way the גמרא Gemara reads it as we'll see in a
minute. רב נחמן Rav Nachman כי מקלע לשכנציב ki mikla le-Shachnatziv מכריז:
makhriz: מאן הויה ליומא? Man havya leyoma? רב נחמן Rav Nachman
would do the same when he would go to this place שכנציב.
Shachnatziv.
So the גמרא Gemara says: ותניא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר לא
ישא אדם אשה במדינה זו וילך וישא אשה במדינה אחרת שמא יזדווגו
זה אצל זה ונמצא אח נושא אחותו ומלא כל הארץ כולה ממזרות.
Ve-tanya Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer lo yisa adam ishah be-medinah zu
ve-yelech ve-yisa ishah be-medinah acheret shema yizdavgu zeh etzel zeh ve-nimtza ach
noseh achoto u-malle ha-aretz kullah mamzerut.
So one minute, but we say that a man is not supposed
to be married to
one woman in one country and another woman in another
country, because then the kids of the two wives will not know
that they're half-siblings and will wind up marrying one another, and then
they'll be transgressing, and the offspring of that incest will be ממזרות.
mamzerut. Okay, so if you're in the same, you know, the wives
are all living together with you in the same house, everybody knows
who their father is. But the fact that you're in one country,
these kids who the father only drops in one month out of
the year and they know their father's name is Sam, and in
another country they know their father's name is Sam, it doesn't mean
they're going to know they have the same father. So you shouldn't
do this. So how could רב Rav go ahead and do this?
So the גמרא Gemara says, or and רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, that's
the גמרא's Gemara only concern. So על זה נאמר ומלאה הארץ זמה,
Al zeh ne'emar u-malah ha-aretz zimah, the land will be filled with
fornication. Okay, so how can you be married to different women in
different countries? They won't know who the father is or they won't
know they share a father. So אמרי, amri, so they can say
רבנן קלי אית להו, Rabbanan kali it le-hu,
the rabbis have a reputation.
Who knows what type of reputation they're getting with this? But their
name is
well-known, and therefore everyone knows it's not just your father happens to
be Sam. Your father is רב, Rav, your father is שמואל. Shmuel.
So with them, then they'll know that when they meet somebody else
and they're talking about getting married and they talk about who their
father is, they'll realize they have the same father. So we're not
concerned about that.
So the גמרא Gemara says: והאמר רבא. Ve-ha-amar Rava.
By the way, I have to say what's interesting is, it says
whenever רב Rav would visit this place, whenever רב נחמן Rav Nachman
would visit this place, they would make the announcement. If they just
did it the first time, then why don't they just have a
wife ready for them in that place? Right? It sounds like every
time they visited this place, they made the announcement. What happens to
the woman you married last time you were there? Maybe that it
supports רבקה's Rifka read that it's not a wife? The גמרא's Gemara
interpreting it as a wife, but it's an interesting point the way
רבקה's Rifka suggesting that it's not in the context of marriage. What?
Or the whole time he was there.
So he would marry her and divorce her the next day. Right.
רש״י Rashi says right. ותצא לאחר מכאן. Ve-teitzei le-achar mikan. רש״י Rashi
says right,
afterwards. Right. So that's a good point. Yeah, I mean, you don't
want that woman bound to him till he visits three years from
now.
It's the rabbi's way of having one-night stands.
Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says, but right, that's a good point,
that רש״י Rashi does mention that he would divorce her afterwards, which
I assume you have to. A, that explains why he would have
to do it every time, but presumably also that would be the
humane thing to do, right?
It's just for the יומא, yoma, I mean when רב Rav says
just for today,
he would go for a day and then fly out on the
red-eye. He went somewhere, stay for a few days.
Right, so that's true, that's true. But again, but the point of
רש״י Rashi saying divorce her not only it solves the issue of
why he would have to do it every time, but it explains
he wouldn't want this woman bound to him. That would be the
humane thing to do, right? Certainly, yeah, I mean, when if you
go for a day and then fly out on the red-eye. Right,
or go somewhere, stay for a few days. Right, so that's true,
that's true, but again, but the point of רש"י's Rashi inverse term,
not only does it solve the issue of why he would have
to do it every time, but it explains, he wouldn't want this
woman to be bound to him between the trips, which presumably would
not be so common. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara has
another question. והאמר רבא—one Ve-ha'amar Rava minute, says didn't רבא Rava say
תבעוה להינשא? Tav'uha lehinasay? Now that's רבא, Rava, this is רב, Rav,
but the גמרא Gemara. assumes that it's all, everybody holds by everyone
else here, so didn't רבא Rava say תבעוה להינשא? Tav'uha lehinasay?
If a man sort of made a demand from his bride to
actually have the nuptials, the marriage itself, meaning what happened would be
they would do the קידושין, Kidushin, he'd give her the ring—I mean,
they didn't have a ring in the time of the גמרא—he'd Gemara
give her whatever he'd give her, she would הלכתית halachically be his
wife, they'd be bound, he should be bound, but they wouldn't start
living together until the חופה. Huppah. And normally there would be about
a year before the חופה Huppah for her to prepare her trousseau
and get ready and for, and so, or maybe even multiple years,
like when they would get married often, get married at a very
young age but not actually start living together until the girl
becomes at least a few years older. So what happens if, here
they are, there's קידושין, Kidushin, there's not נישואין, Nissuin, and he comes
to her and says, "That's it, I'm tired of waiting, let's have
our חופה Huppah next week"? So the הלכה Halakha, is is that
once he made this demand to get married, she would all of
a sudden become desirous and start thinking about the fact that they'll
be together and be having sex, and the גמרא Gemara says ונתפייסה—if
Venitpaisah she agrees, ונתפייסה, Venitpaisah, she agrees—so because there's a suddenness to
it and then she agrees, so because of that suddenness and that
shock value, צריכה לישב שבעה נקיים. Tzericha leishev shiva neki'im. She has
to wait seven days, meaning seven clean days without blood, because we're
afraid that the excitement and the suddenness led to her to spot,
and therefore, even if you don't see any blood, and therefore she
becomes a נדה Niddah and therefore she needs seven clean days. This
is called דם חימוד. Dam Chimud. Now this is a fascinating topic
in itself. First of all, some have suggested that this was the
רבנן, Rabbanan what's it called,
transferring their male experience to the women. So the same way we
were talking before about men getting sexually excited and having seminal emission,
the גמרא Gemara says, oh maybe the woman when she gets sexually
excited has some spotting. Okay, so transferring that sort of reality to
the women might be what this assumption that there's this דם חימוד.
Dam Chimud. This also is why, I don't know if people are
aware, the whole practice about making sure you don't go to the
מקווה—a Mikvah כלה—more Kallah than four days before the wedding. There's, I
don't know if people are aware of this הלכה, Halakha. and without
getting into the details, some of it has to do with the
fact that you want to make sure like that you're טהור tahor
and you're checking yourself, whatever, until right up until the wedding because
the oncoming event of the wedding leads to this concern about דם
חימוד. Dam Chimud. Now there are some ראשונים Rishonim that basically say
that a woman has to be checking herself every single day after
having gone to the מקווה Mikvah until the wedding because we're concerned
that as the wedding is getting closer, it's increasing the sexual desire.
But there's a whole other group of ראשונים Rishonim which is primarily
the way we rule, that only emphasizes the suddenness of this idea,
תבעוה להינשא. Tav'uha lehinasay. He sprang it on her, it was sudden,
and it's the shock and the suddenness that lead to that concern,
but once you're building up to the wedding and you know it's
coming and you sent out the invitations, that is not that concern.
So this is a principle called דם חימוד, Dam Chimud, a rabbinic
idea. So it says if this is true, how could they get—how,
when he says, "Let's get married today," or רבקה, Rifka, here it
would work even without marriage, "Let's have sex today," if that suddenness
leads to a concern of spotting, then how could they have sex
on the same day? Okay. So the גמרא says,
רבנן אדויי
הוו מודעי להו, Rabbanan adoyi havei modyi lehu, so the רבנן would
inform them ahead of time. מקדם הוו מקדמי ומשדרי שלוחא, Mikdam havei
makdimi umashaderei shlucha, and then they would go ahead and send a
messenger. So that changes the whole story. It wouldn't be רב Rav
would arrive at the airport and make an announcement, but he would
send somebody like a little אליעזר, Eliezer, or better than אליעזר, Eliezer,
a better example is
יהודה and רעהו העדולמי—well, Re'ehu ha-Adulami that was actually to seal the
deal after the
fact, but to pay up anyway—but you would send somebody ahead of
time to scout out and to find the woman for him. So
that woman would have time before he arrived to go to the
מקווה Mikvah and count the seven days and so on. That's the
גמרא's answer. No longer is he making the announcement, he's sending someone
ahead to prepare to find the woman and to prepare it.
So איבעית אימא, I-ba'is eima, and if you want another answer is,
יחודי הוו מיחדי להו. Yichudi havei miyachadi lehu. They would have ייחוד
Yichud with them. What does that mean? Let me read and then
I'll explain. לפי שאינו דומה מי שיש לו פת בסלו למי שאין
לו פת בסלו. Lefi she-eino domeh mi she-yesh lo pas besalo le-mi
she-ein lo pas besalo. It's not different, somebody who has bread in
his basket, somebody who doesn't have bread in his basket, which basically
רש"י Rashi says what it means is they wouldn't have sex. So
רש"י Rashi says by the end the גמרא is really cleaning it
up. רבקה Rifka said they cleaned it up by turning this issue
of "today" into an idea of marriage, but according to the end
now they're really cleaning it up because saying oh they actually would
never actually have sex, they would just sort of say, "You'll be
my wife, and I know I'm able to have sex with you
if I want to," and therefore because I know it's available to
me, I'm not going to bother to do it, because it's פת
בסלו, pas besalo, I know it's available. I don't have that sense
of desire isn't as powerful once it's actually available. Now תוספות Tosfos
doesn't like this answer
because
תוספות Tosfos says right in your basket you eat it.
Well, that's true, but also,
what do you mean available? If you can't be having sex because
you're afraid that she's a נדה because of this דם חימוד, Dam
Chimud, so it's not available during this week that you're here. So
what's going on here? So he gives another answer.
It sounds like it's all of this talks about what? Bread of
the שעיר העזאזל, Seir Ha'azazel, right? The same thing, the same concept.
Yeah, the whole idea of פת בסלו Pas Basalo comes from the
bread that they would prepare for the כהן Cohen and for the
שעיר העזאזל, Seir Ha'azazel, right?
The bread they would what do you mean the bread?
It was פת בסלו. Pas Basalo.
Were those the קלפים? klafim?
No, no, when the guy isn't this the guy who took the
שעיר העזאזל Seir Ha'azazel would have bread with him?
Yes, oh he'd have bread at oh right right right, you're right,
yeah. Yeah, there'd be food available for him to eat and once
there's food available for him to eat, he doesn't feel as urgent.
But he doesn't eat it.
He could eat it. But you feel that it's available. Now actually
that's an interesting question. Some actually say he could eat it. We'll
discuss that when we get to that, but that's an interesting point.
Anyway, it's a very strange conclusion in this
גמרא. רש"י says דאין מסקקין להן, d'ein miskakin lahen, okay, you know,
so you could have sex but they actually wouldn't. The ר"י Ri
tries to clean it up even more and the ר"י Ri actually
says that when they came they didn't make the announcement who wants
to marry me and have sex with me, they just said who
wants to be able to have יחוד Yichud with me, be with
me for the day. And because they didn't say that we're going
to have sex, they only said we're going to have יחוד, Yichud,
we'll be able to be together, share a bedroom, so there wouldn't
be a דם חימוד Dam Chimud because then he wouldn't mention sex.
And then if in the middle of the night it turned out
that it evolves into sex, at least then it wouldn't be this
דם חימוד Dam Chimud where you make this announcement I'm looking, you
know, that I'm interested in finding a woman who wants to be
able to who wants to have sex. So anyway, the fascinating answers
here at the end. I think Rivka makes a good point about
that it's the גמרא's interpretation that this was about marriage. And it
is also interesting the parallel about, you know, the whole concern about
seminal emission and then talking about how these rabbis try to sort
of deal with it in a sort of somewhat kosher way.
And I do think also the mention about the bleeding when a
woman is sexually excited, that concern might create an interesting sort of
parallel to the concern of men's sexual excitement and them having seminal
emission. Let's finish by reading the משנה. מסרו זקני בית דין לזקני
כהונה. Masru ziknei Beis Din le-ziknei kehuna. So now it's transferred from
the בית דין, Beis Din, those that represent תורה Torah authority or
those that represent כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, and they gave him over
to the כהנים, Kohanim, to the elders of the כהנים, Kohanim, so
the כהן Cohen authority. העלוהו לבית אבטינס. He-elu-hu l'beis Avtinas. They brought
him to בית אבטינס, Beis Avtinas, which is where they made the
קטורת. Ketores. Okay, because now they're going to have to teach him
how to do the קטורת, Ketores, which was a very difficult עבודה.
avoda And also, as you might be aware, the קטורת Ketores there
was a big debate. The Sadducees, right, said that you put the
קטורת Ketores on the fire before you walk into the קודש הקודשים,
Kodesh Hakodashim, and the rabbis, the פרושים, Perushim, said you go into
the קודש הקודשים Kodesh Hakodashim and then you put it on the
fire. And they were very concerned because there was a lot of
Sadducees, a lot of כהנים Kohanim were Sadducees, presumably mostly most of
the כהנים, Kohanim, and therefore there was a big concern how the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would act on יום כיפור. So it says
like this: So they brought him to this place where they did
the קטורת. Ketores. והשביעוהו, V'hishpi-uhu, and they made him take an oath.
And the oath is we're going to see in a minute. ונפטרו
והלכו להם, Viniftru v'halchu lahem, and then the they left, the זקני
בית דין ziknei Beis Din left after they made him take an
oath. ואמרו לו, V'amru lo, and they said to him: אישי כהן
גדול, Ishi Kohen Gadol, Mr. כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, אנו שלוחי
בית דין, anu shluchei Beis Din, we represent בית דין, Beis Din,
ואתה שלוחנו ושליח בית דין, v'ata shlucheinu u-shliach Beis Din, and you
are our representative and the representative of בית דין. Beis Din. Getting
interesting בית דין, Beis Din, presumably that means כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael,
okay. משביעין אנו עליך במי ששיכן שמו בבית הזה, Mashbi'in anu alecha
b'mi she-shachan shemo babayis hazeh, we impose upon you an oath in
the name of the one whose name dwells in this house. The
מהרש"א Maharsha says that this is an echo of the פסוק pasuk
about השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם, hashochen itam betoch tumasam, which is a
פסוק pasuk by יום כיפור that we cleanse the אהל מועד, Ohel
Moed, and the God who is השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם. shochen itam
betoch tumasam.
בית דין של מעלה, Beis Din shel mala, בית דין של מטה,
Beis Din shel mata, הוא שליח בית דין של מטה? hu shliach
Beis Din shel mata?
Maybe,
although I don't see that in the משנה. Okay, שלא תשנה דבר
מכל מה שאמרנו לך, shelo teshaneh davar mikol mah she-amarnu lach, that
you won't change anything from everything we taught you. We've been teaching
you how to do the עבודה avodah and how to do the
קטורת. Ketores. We make you take an oath that you will do
exactly as you said and not do the קטורת Ketores in the
Sadducee way. הוא פורש ובוכה והם פורשים ובוכין. Hu poresh v'bocheh v'hem
porshim v'bochin. He would go off and cry that he was suspected,
and they would go off and cry that they were forced to
suspect him. אם היה חכם דורש. Im haya chacham doreish. If he
was wise now here how he has to stay up the whole
night. If he was wise, he would give a שיעור. shiur. ואם
לאו, V'im lav, and if he's not smart enough to give a
שיעור shiur but smart enough to understand a שיעור, shiur, תלמידי חכמים
דורשין לפניו. talmidei chachamim darshin lefanav. You'd have sages... notice of course
it's all the rabbinic presence. Sages giving him a שיעור. shiur. ואם
רגיל לקרות, Ve'im ragil likrot, now let's say having a שיעור shiur
in גמרא is beyond him, okay obviously it means not גמרא here
but הלכה. So then read something from תנ"ך. Tanakh. So if he's
familiar with reading קורא, korei, find a ספר sefer of תנ"ך Tanakh
to read and keep you interested. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, if he's
not so good and fluent in Hebrew, קורין לפניו, korin lefanav, you'd
get people to read to him. So we're going down levels: the
ability to do it yourself, the ability to understand from a sort
of rabbinic type of learning to reading the פסוקים. pesukim. ובמה קורין
לפניו? Uve'meh korin lefanav? What would they read for him? Now we're
dealing clearly with the most ignorant that they couldn't even read תנ"ך
Tanakh themselves. What would they read him? באיוב ובעזרא ובדברי הימים. Be'Iyov
uve'Ezra uve'Divrei HaYamim. איוב Iyov and עזרא Ezra and דברי הימים. Divrei
HaYamim. So דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim you're saying, "What? That is so
boring!" put you to sleep. But it would have—it depends which sections
of it. עזרא Ezra would be in Aramaic and that and that
because Aramaic was the vernacular. So that and עזרא's Ezra an interesting
story and it's relevant to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and it's
all a good narrative, עזרא. Ezra. איוב Iyov is maybe for those
that are more philosophically minded. זכריה בן קבוטל אומר פעמים הרבה קראתי
לפניו בדניאל, Zecharya ben Kevutal omer: pa'amim harbeh karisi lefanav be'Daniel, which
is also really good stories in דניאל, Daniel, so these would keep
them engaged. I want to just end by saying: who made him
take the oath about the קטורת? Ketoret? The משנה's ambiguous, right? It
says והלכו להם ואמרו לו. ve'halchu lahem ve'amru lo. Is it the
זקני בית דין Ziknei Beit Din before they left this is what
they said to him? Or did the זקני בית דין Ziknei Beit
Din left and now the elders of the כהנים, Kohanim, the זקני
הכהונה, Ziknei HaKehunah, made him take the שבועה? shevuah? And there's a
debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. The רמב"ן Ramban actually says that it's
the זקני בית דין Ziknei Beit Din that made him take the
שבועה, shevuah, not the זקני כהונה, Ziknei Kehunah, which in a way
makes sense because you're still having that rabbinic presence ensuring and supervising
the כהנים Kohanim and making sure that you do the עבודה the
way the פרושים Perushim say and not the way the צדוקים Tzadukim
say. As opposed to saying the rabbis left and then it was
left to the זקני כהנים Ziknei Kohanim to make him take an
oath. That creates a slightly different type of a framing of exactly
what happened. Okay, and with that.